moveon.org 2019-10-17

# Privacy Policy | MoveOn.Org | Democracy In Action

This website, http://civic.moveon.org (the “Site”) is operated by MoveOn.org Civic Action (“We” or “Us”). **We work hard to protect your privacy.** We’re members too, and we treat your privacy as we do our own. We wrote this privacy policy to let you know how we treat your personal information – and to show you all the ways we work to keep it safe and private.

If at any time you would like to unsubscribe from our email list, you may do so by [completing this form.](https://act.moveon.org/unsubscribe/unsubscribe/) The Site is directed to users in the United States only.

MoveOn.org will send you updates by e-mail. You may be contacted by phone to coordinate your participation in MoveOn events. We do not share the information you’ve given us with unaffiliated groups without your explicit permission. We may share some of your personal information with the following affiliated groups:

  * MoveOn.org Political Action, our sister organization;
  * MoveOn.org Education Fund;
  * Affiliated Third Parties – for example, our database administrators or organizations that provide extra organizers at an urgent time – for the sole purpose of helping Us do our work. These groups do not share your personal information or use it for any purpose other than as instructed by Us.
  * Third Party Administrators, such as organizations we engage to facilitate large distribution of messages. The content of these emails will be from MoveOn.org Civic 
  * Action and these third parties do not have direct access to your personally identifiable information.

**In addition, with your explicit permission, we pass along certain of your information to the following groups (as is standard practice):**

  * The President, legislators and news publications and other targets when you choose to use our email tool to send them messages;
  * With the President, legislators, news publications, and the general public when you sign petitions or complete surveys;

Under circumstances where we determine that members may be misusing our systems for malicious purposes (for example, using the numbers we provide to make harassing phone calls), such activities may be reported to law enforcement agencies. In such cases, MoveOn may release personally identifiable information, including name and address, to those agencies.

Please review this privacy policy periodically because we modify it from time to time. This privacy policy was last revised on August 13, 2019. Each time you visit this Site or provide us with information through the Site, by doing so you are accepting practices described in the privacy policy in effect at that time. You are also accepting our specific rules or terms of use which may be posted on specific sections of the Site, including areas for making donations, signing petitions or sending emails, and taking part in our photo campaigns.

This privacy policy applies to transactions and activities in which you engage and data gathered only on the Site. **This privacy policy does not apply to any other website or any offline contact between MoveOn.org Civic Action and any other entity or offline contact between you and MoveOn.org Civic Action.**

MoveOn does not collect or maintain any personal data from any persons not resident in the U.S. or in U.S. territories or possessions. Thus MoveOn does not collect or maintain any personal data from any EU data subjects within the meaning of the General Data Protection Regulation. If you believe that MoveOn has collected personal data from you and you are outside the United States, U.S. territories and possessions, please contact MoveOn at the contact link provided at the end of this Privacy Policy, and MoveOn will remove such data from its records, and contact you to confirm that has been done.

**Sharing of Information Between MoveOn.org Civic Action and MoveOn.org Political Action**

MoveOn.org Civic Action is a 501(c)(4) organization that primarily focuses on nonpartisan education and advocacy on important national issues. MoveOn.org Political Action is a federal political committee that primarily helps members elect candidates who reflect our values through a variety of activities aimed at influencing the outcome of the next election. MoveOn.org Civic Action and MoveOn.org Political Action are separate organizations. However, they’re both interested in promoting your participation in the democratic process. As such, when you provide your personal information to MoveOn.org Civic Action , we share it with MoveOn.org Political Action (and vice versa), with the exception of credit card information with which you may provide us in order to make a donation. Please see the Financial Donations section, below, for more information about donations.

**Petitions and Surveys**

You may visit the Site and review some of its contents without providing any personal information to MoveOn. To create or sign a petition, to make comments, or to upload content, such as photographs, on MoveOn’s petition website, you will be asked to become a member of the Site (“Member”), and must provide information including but not limited to your first name, last name, zip code, phone number, email address (“Personal Information”).

For petitions and surveys you’ve signed, created or completed, we treat your name, city, state, and comments as public information – for example, we may provide compilations of petitions, with your comments, to the President and legislators, other targets, or to the press. We will not make your street address publicly available, but we may transmit it to your petition targets as part of a petition. This is a standard industry practice in such situations. In no such case will we disclose your email address or phone number without your permission. We may also make your comments, along with your first name, city, and state available to the press and public online.

Your Personal Information will be shared with MoveOn.org Civic Action and MoveOn.org Political Action (the “MoveOn Entities”), but only Public Petition Information will be available to the public.

If you become a Member, MoveOn may send you updates about the Site and about any petition you created or signed by email. If you sign a petition on the Site, you may also receive emails from the creator of that petition (the “Petitioner”). You can remove yourself from the MoveOn mailing lists at any time by following the instructions contained in any email communication you receive.

If you have expressed a desire to participate in the activities on the Site, you may be contacted by phone to coordinate your participation with MoveOn’s petition website or other MoveOn activities. Unless you provide it directly, no Petitioner will have access to your phone information. [Click here if you would like to be removed permanently from our phone list.](https://act.moveon.org/survey/sms-unsubscribe/)

**Sending Emails Via MoveOn.org Civic Action**

In certain cases, we enable you to send individual e-mails to the President, legislators, and other targets as well as Letters-to-the-Editor to various news publications, through our website. These messages are sent in your name, with your e-mail address as the return address and your full name and contact information is provided as part of the submission. These messages will only be sent out under your name as you approve them on an individual basis using our email tool. You are solely responsible for the specific message(s) you send using our email tool.

**Sending Emails Via MoveOn’s Petition Website**

In certain cases, we enable Petitioners to send individual emails to signers of petitions they have created, the president, legislators, and other targets as well as letters to the editor to various news publications, through our website.

These messages are sent in the Petitioner’s name, with the Petitioner’s email address as the return address and the Petitioner’s full name and contact information is provided as part of the submission. These messages will be sent out under the Petitioner’s name only as the Petitioner approves them on an individual basis using our email messaging tool. If you would like to change the email return address, you can do so by emailing petitions@moveon.org. 

If you are a Petitioner, you are solely responsible for the specific message(s) you send using our email tool.

**Financial Donations**

MoveOn treats our donors’ credit card information with the highest level of privacy and security, following industry best practices. Our donation pages use a secure (SSL/https) connection to send credit card data directly to a leading payment processor that is certified Payment Card Industry (PCI) compliant. MoveOn never has access to or stores credit card numbers in any format on any of our servers.

**Phone Campaigns**

From time to time, MoveOn.org staff members, volunteers, and vendors may contact you by telephone about urgent campaigns. If you would like to be removed permanently from our phone list, please [click here](https://front.moveon.org/frequently-asked-questions-about-outreach/). Please allow 8-10 business days for your information to be removed.

**Children**

MoveOn.org Civic Action does not solicit personally identifying information from children. Visitors who are under 13 years of age should ask their parent or legal guardian for assistance when using the Site and should not submit any personally identifying information to the Site. For example, visitors under 13 years of age should not make donations or use the MoveOn.org Civic Action email tool.

**Cookies**

Some parts of the Site are password-protected. If you check “Remember Me” upon log-in, we will use a cookie (cookies reside on your computer and are under the control of your browser) to enable you to return to password-protected areas of the website without having to re-enter your password. If you wish to disable these cookies, the help portion of the tool bar on most browsers will tell you how do that. If you set your browser to disable cookies, however, you may not be able to access certain parts of this Site.

**Advertising**

We may place online advertising with third-party vendors, including Google, which will be shown on other sites on the internet. In some cases, those third-party vendors may decide which ads to show you based on your prior visits to the Site. If you prefer to opt out of the use of these third-party cookies on the Site, you can do so by visiting the [Network Advertising Initiative opt out page](http://www.networkadvertising.org/choices/).

**Data Tracking**

In order to better serve our members, we use cookies and periodically analyze web logs. We may also use third-party services such as Google Analytics. This helps us understand traffic patterns and know if there are problems with our website. We may also use embedded images in emails to track open rates for our mailings, so that we can tell which mailings appeal most to MoveOn.org Civic Action members.

URLs contained in emails may contain an ID that enables us to correctly identify the person who takes an action using a web page. We use these URLs to simplify the process of signing petitions and filling out surveys. We may occasionally present a shortened URL that references a longer URL which contains an id—we do this to simplify the display, to prevent links from becoming broken when copied, and to ensure compatibility with email programs which do not handle long URLs. When a shortened URL is displayed in an email, you will see the full URL in the browser’s address bar when you access the page.

**Non-Personally Identifiable Information**

We may share aggregate information about who and where our members are with third parties including, but not limited to, legislators, partner organizations, and political campaigns. This information will be disclosed in aggregate form only and will not, under any circumstances, contain personally identifiable information. Examples of this type of aggregate data include, but are not limited to, how many MoveOn members live in a town, or how many new people from a particular state have joined MoveOn this year. We may also use such aggregate information to analyze trends, administer the Site, and gather broad demographic information for aggregate use.

**Links to Other Websites**

MoveOn.org Civic Action may provide links to third party websites, and other websites may provide links to the Site. Third party websites operate according to their own terms of use and privacy policies. MoveOn.org Civic Action has no control over such third party websites, and by using this Site, you acknowledge and agree that MoveOn.org Civic Action is not responsible for the availability of such third party sites, and does not endorse and is not responsible or liable for any content, advertising, products or other materials on or available from such sites. You further acknowledge and agree that MoveOn.org Civic Action will not be responsible or liable, directly or indirectly, for any damage or loss caused or alleged to be caused by or in connection with use of or reliance on any content, advertising, products, or other materials on or available from such sites.

**Changes to the Privacy Policy**

MoveOn.org Civic Action may revise or amend this policy at any time at our sole discretion. If we make any substantive changes in the way we collect or use personally identifying information provided by users, we will post a prominent announcement on our website home page and post the changes on this page. We will never change our policies and practices to make them less protective of user information collected prior to the effective date of any changes without the consent of affected users. We encourage users to visit this page periodically to review our current policy.

**Contact**

If you have any questions about this privacy statement, your personal information, or the practices of this Site, you can [contact us](https://front.moveon.org/frequently-asked-questions-and-contact-information-2/).

**Email from MoveOn.org Civic Action**

MoveOn will send you updates on this and other important campaigns by email. If at any time you would like to unsubscribe from our email list, you may do so by [completing this form.](https://act.moveon.org/unsubscribe/unsubscribe/)
